software engineering radio episode 23
architecture problem
[Music]
okay welcome to this new episode of
software engineering radio this one is
the first episode on software
architecture and it's something we tried
for the first time this is basically a
skype teleconference with three people
so this is me Marcus then we have Alex
hi and we here hello there
okay so yeah software architecture this
is a very big topic and we'll need
several episodes to cover it in this
first episode we'll talk about the
fundamentals this includes the role of
the Software Architect and what software
architecture is after all to get the
discussion started let's come up with a
definition of what software architecture
is and and let's see whether we the
three of us agree on that so in the
American Heritage Dictionary I found the
definition about what is architecture
and it says the art and science of
designing and erecting buildings a style
and method of designing construction and
the orderly management of parts so if we
transfer that to software architecture
who would say that software architecture
basically is the art and science of
designing and building software a style
and method of design and construction as
well as the early management or
arrangement of paths anybody disagrees
no I think essentially it covers the
core of it
when I get asked in my consulting
activities to define what architectures
then I mostly refer to first
responsibilities functionalities that my
system has to fulfill secondly two
interactions two dependencies between
those responsibilities and thirdly two
interfaces between those
responsibilities due to the dependencies
due to the interactions and that is
basically all I need for for doing
architecture and well the the hard
problem with with doing architecture is
to fulfill all the forces all basically
didn't
the non-functional concerns
non-functional requirements that are
implied on my system and as an architect
I try to balance those rights
architectures always a compromise Alex I
think you want to say something about
software architecture versus the other
kinds of architecture are necessary when
building systems exactly one point
architect or software architect is a
heavily used term right now so almost
everybody calls him an architect but
what we really discuss your software
architecture and software architects and
there are many other architects out
there their IT architects business
architects integration Enterprise
architects and every architect does
another thing here's another
responsibility and yeah actually anyway
let me give one example of such another
responsibility let's begin with an IT
architect for example the IT architect
usually is responsible for
infrastructure for hardware for network
topologies and therefore for the
infrastructure stuff the an enterprise
architecture is the overall architect
who keeps all the things working
together the the software architecture
the IT architecture business
architecture and so on an enterprise
software architect on the other hand is
a software architect that does huge
software systems enterprise ready
software systems so they these
architects have very very different
roles in an enterprise or in a company
and very often these get mixed up so we
have to clearly discuss what a software
architect is here in our podcasts I
guess right so in this podcast we cover
software architecture we do not look at
the other kinds of architectures we
might cover them in later episodes yeah
before we go on can I maybe offer
another definition of what architecture
is or what software architecture is and
that would be everything that I care
about in a project that should be
standardized or done in a similar
fashion would you say that this is a
sensor
definition of architecture yeah
definitely I mean that is part of the
the result the role of an architect that
you have to ensure consistency and with
the software architecture at a high
level you ensure this consistency what I
like about this kind of definition is
for me architecture actually is a pretty
fuzzy a conceptual thing I mean we have
code and architecture is within the code
but it's not something explicit we don't
have an explicit or divided architecture
thing it's it's just a it's like a
structural thing or whatever so maybe
this also leads us to the distinction
between design and architecture exactly
so if I say that architecture is
everything that I care about that should
be standardized and and consistent then
design is maybe everything on a
granularity level below that right
exactly that I totally agree with that
design for me is one level below
architecture and wherever you start with
your architecture design is below is
so-so
architecture is for me as at the top
level guiding the brooch guiding the
system guiding the software under
development with rules with design
guidelines with design principles to
adhere to with architectural styles and
architectural patterns that guide that
shape the the overall software system at
the lower layer you would then have the
design where you talk about individual
classes or you talk about objects
variables and all those things but is
there actually some kind of border where
does design and an architecture begin or
other way around
yeah that's maybe the trig of this
definition I offered because if I say I
don't care whether somebody implements
something using the observer pattern or
in another way then it's designed
because it's it's on a level that's not
critical for for example the
non-functional requirement
for my system it's not important that
it's done in a standardized way if I
want it to be done in a specific way to
realize certain requirements then I say
it's architecture yes in the kind of a
self-fulfilling definition and this
contradicts a bit the granularity thing
I mean it's it's more the importance you
say okay right well the indicator if
it's a design or architecture so you say
in some cases you might have to make
architectural decisions that are quite
fine granular quiet exactly yeah exactly
so let's briefly touch upon some process
issues in the agile world the term
architect and architecture is somewhat
disliked people say agile projects don't
need an architecture or don't need an
architect any opinions on that I don't
think they say an eighth or in a nature
project you don't have an architecture
all the systems I've seen that are done
with extreme programming for example
have an architecture and mostly a very
very good architecture so they have a
structure they have an architecture they
have important design decisions to stay
with your definition what they not so
often have is an explicit architect as a
role so I guess there is the the huge
difference between the traditional
software development projects or pro
methods and HR projects yeah I would put
it that way that in a child reject the
architecture is not explicitly bland but
much more created by having always a
running system starting with a small
core starting with the areas of highest
risk and then defining the architecture
implicitly while developing the working
system and that the architecture grows
as you complete your system and still I
believe it's it's important to pick the
right architectural patterns for you for
this core for the initial working system
to then be able to grow that system and
not having to refactor your whole
solution to match the later requirements
when you when you increase when you grow
your system exactly that's a very
important point there the timing is
different from traditional software
projects or methods they usually do all
the architecture stuff in front of the
project front up and RHI projects try to
avoid design and architectural decisions
as long as possible
they they try to decide at the latest
responsible moment in the project so it
feels different but there still is
architecture and architectural work of
course so there is maybe a difference
between the architecture as an artefact
that you might want to create at the
beginning of a project which consists of
paper basically and you monograms or
whatever and then the architecture is
something that you can extract from an
existing system so something that grows
over time and the agile folks say we
don't want to do this upfront thing but
rather make sure the architecture
evolves over time exactly and this is
one of the similarities between these
different architect types with our type
of architects we talked before usually
if you have an architect you have to
distinguish between the actual
architecture the architecture of the
software system and fuse of the
architecture and it may be you do the
fuse front up into the design and the
architecture front up and do UML
diagrams or whatever but you also can do
it later on the project or after the
even after the project is a post-mortem
so the fuse of the architecture and
there are many few there are statics use
dynamics use whatever are not the
architecture itself but if I want to
come up with a consistent system and and
and also if I say I don't want to
pre-plan the architecture rather I want
to evolve it over time or over the cause
of the project if I want to be it to be
consistent how do i how do I make sure
that in such an agile approach a
consistent system evolves then
I think having having guidelines and
having as few as possible principles
that are accepted by all developers
involved can help with that
so for example only asynchronous
communication is involved in the whole
system and no synchronous communication
because you need to be highly reactive
and and you're in embedded real-time
environment so if you just prohibit the
use of synchronous communication dead
already saves you a lot of trouble and
in many design decisions can be derived
from that principle so you say that that
you also have a number of guiding
principles even in those agile projects
but you don't spend I don't know two
months and and write this big
architecture document upfront yes that's
the point okay and another thing is you
usually try to keep your code and
therefore your architecture but but
mostly your code in a state where you
can change it easily and the easier it
is to change the code or exit for
example the dry the don't repeat your
self thing if you have to just change
little parts of the systems to do act
actual architectural changes it's easier
for you to change the architecture and
to be honest even if in the non h-hi
projects I I were in we had to change
some architectural stuff later on so
architecture can't be really static it
shouldn't be in my opinion actually so
you should do everything to make it
flexible and changeable and so on so
it's basically not possible to come up
with an architecture up front you might
be able to start you know start with a
good a good starting point using
architectural patterns or something
which we'll talk about in later episodes
but it always has to evolve yeah it's a
bit different in well product lines or
something like that where you just can
copy an architecture that already is
proven in this area but in in normal non
complex systems you can't come up with a
arty
just run up that that really hits the
point and doesn't have to be changed on
the way so me hey do we need an
architect yes I I agree I well I think
the role of an architect is is often
overvalued and maybe misunderstood so it
almost seems like it's the the most
honour of the developers to become an
architect I will have this set on my
business card right and so I think every
developers as valuable as an architect I
actually kind of dislike there's this
ownership but still I think somebody in
the team must be responsible to ensure
consistency to facilitate communication
to ensure reuse and to coach others in a
project and if I would have to give this
person a name it's it's of course the
architect yes there is always this
discussion whether there should be one
architect or whether there should be a
group of people who do the architecture
and and that's maybe somewhat there's
maybe an analogy that people say that
this is saying that says nice systems or
well-designed systems are the product of
a simple brilliant mind or something
like that you might have heard about
this statement so do we need to have one
architect to make sure that everything
is consistent in a way that he thinks or
or or do we have a group of architects
or how does this work or or can this be
done in different ways in different
projects I think for for small teams one
person one architect is totally
sufficient but for big projects and and
projects distributed over several
locations which is the the common case
in my company that I work for you have
typically a group of architects and the
the important point here is to have only
one lead architect so it's kind of a
hierarchical system that I suggest so
for example for every subsystem have a
have an architect or well not for every
subsystem but try to minimize the number
of architects but when distributing the
architects associate with them
individual subsystems and then have one
lead architect that has the final saying
when there's dispute when there's
disagreement on design decisions and
also it might probably make sense to in
big systems to have architects that are
experts in certain technologies like for
example if you use carbon then you might
want to have somebody who you might want
to call carbon architect or middleware
architect or something who deals with
technology specifics right and also well
what I just said we're splitting
according to subsystems splitting
according to layers is also something
that is very common right okay to
summarize what we discussed so far
why does a system need a software
architecture so first of all it resolves
conflicting forces in a specific way a
software architecture as we said before
it's almost always a compromise it also
serves as a guideline for more detailed
design decisions so the design decisions
that developers or teams make on their
own have to be compatible or in line
with the architecture so that helps to
create a consistence of the system as a
consequence the architecture also leads
to a well-defined programming model a
programming model is a term that we'll
discuss later I guess and it basically
means that if you want to implement
business logic based on a certain
architectural style or on a certain
architecture then the programming model
defines how you implement that business
logic the architecture can also serve as
a basis for a software system family
which is also something we discussed
later in the context of product line
engineering a software architecture also
helps to define the basic building floor
metaphors for the system or even a
vocabulary that can be used to discuss
about the system in the team so before
we go on to additional observations
observations I think it's important that
in a team the architecture is something
that everybody feels responsible for it
doesn't make too much sense if you have
this guru architect who you know always
make sure the documents are nice but
nobody cares about that and also usually
an architecture as we said has to be
built incrementally it evolves over time
over time during a project though the
number of changes and the severity of
changes should become less frequent
otherwise your initial software
architecture was probably wrong and the
experience of a software architect shows
basically by experience of the
architects more often get it right or
relatively right in the beginning so
that's basically a summary of what we
discussed till now
we should probably now discuss in a bit
more detail the tasks that a software
architect has to has to execute the
things that he's responsible for in a
software project so we go from software
architecture as the thing we built to
the task of architecting a system to the
responsibility of software architect so
when I as I just introduced when I talk
about software architects I always think
about bigger projects or projects that
have a size of at least 15 to 20
developers and so here is already a
problem that I see that is the
scalability of the role I mean a kind of
single person and the due to all the
design decision should a single person
do all the design architecture decision
or should much more the team collaborate
and define the architecture commonly and
should basically one person then ensure
the consistency of it so
this has also to do with scalability
getting having teams at the size of like
50 developers even hundred developers
working on the software project you need
to way to scale the role of often
architect and so to achieve the
scalability
I generally define the priorities of an
architect like that so first he has to
communicate with the stakeholders so
this is product management general
management this is what the requirements
folks with the customer if necessary and
of course between the teams with the
teams with the developers and what he
should share are the requirements the
design guidelines the principles that
the whole development team should adhere
to secondly for the second priority he
should ensure the consistency of the
overall architecture by reviewing the
design made by the individual developers
so this is for me this is a key here
because well when I'm in a team I trust
the developers that I do good design
decisions having the basic principles at
hand and doing regular reviews ensures
that all the design decisions go along
and smooth and towards the same goal to
achieve to the product success right so
reviews is not a sign of mistrust
it's rather just a way to make sure that
people have compatible decisions right
yes
okay and and the third priority is
guiding the developers and doing good
design there might be some team members
that are not so experienced and and
coaching them doing design calmly with
them being on the whiteboard and
discussing things is very valuable for
them and you also then get a good
feeling for how the developers think
about the design how to design decisions
God defined how they got worked out and
only at the with the lease priority you
would contribute your own design but
knowledge because you're the the main
flow of your experience into the project
should come through the reviews and so
with this as I had already a good
success in the past and was able to to
lead even big projects as a technical
lead as an architect it's probably a
tough one for those guru architects who
always want to show that they're the
best technical geeks and the best
experts on something if you say that
they should contribute their knowledge
only on priority for yeah it might be
kind of disappointing to them but I
believe the amount of developers the
amount of brain working there is it's
much larger this way than having only
one guru architect for me the best way
to to scale our key texts in a project
were yeah actually if you have more than
one architect and of course you should
have this lead architect you already
thought about but then the the single
architect should concentrate on
different architectural well components
or layers or whatever so you you should
give an architect a responsibility for
an architectural thing whatever this
thing means this is better for
identification with the topic and I made
the best of the best results with this
kind of scaling there so one thing where
it's probably a good idea to have
separate architects or people or
technical leads is for certain
technologies I think we agree on that
yeah but in my opinion you shouldn't
have a trust corbin architect that
doesn't know anything about the rest of
the application right so it you should
actually integrate the the discussion or
the the people along architectural
things whatever this me
asset components or whatever so yes you
need architects with different skill
sets but they shouldn't be really
separated along these technical topics I
would yeah I have actually worked on
projects what we just had this database
architect and then this middleware
architect and this was actually their
their the also the organizational thing
that the one just cared for the database
and the other didn't know anything about
the database and that was a huge
communication problem and it never
really fits together so I'm not so sure
if this is a good way to organize the
architects but of course you should have
people with different special skill sets
yeah I I also know a company a
consulting comedy in Germany that splits
the roles of architects along
infrastructure architects and
application architects so the
infrastructure architects would care
about all the middleware communication a
database persistency etc and the
application architects would then
actually deal with the customer
requirements with implementing the
application logic on top of that and I
always ask myself whether that is a good
split whether they for some of the
infrastructure architects have the right
understanding of the problem to to make
the right design decisions to whether
they know all the forces imposed on the
software system as a whole that's
exactly the point
if these Bose architects don't have to
know or understand what the other does
for that job and the the architecture as
things are that separated that it works
it can work if the middleware architect
actually doesn't have to know anything
about the the other things in the system
and the the business logic or whatever
which is unlike work but this exactly
this is very very unlikely and then I
have I have had a lot of trouble
with these kinds of separation so we so
I think we agree that it's not a good
idea to have technical geeks like you
know do their own thing and don't care
about the rest and that's probably true
for most systems I think there is an
exception and and that is something
we'll discuss in further episodes and
that is in the context of product lines
or software system families where you
explicitly want to build and evolve a
platform that can basically carry many
different applications there usually
have a domain architect a person who
takes care of the of the fundamentals of
the product line and then you have for
each project that you built on top of
the product line you have application
architects but actually even there I
would always try to get someone into
this well however we call it
infrastructure architectures things who
knows the domain stuff yes sir all
salutely you do need domain architects
they are different from the specific
application architect yeah and here the
difference is also the main architects
doesn't mean infrastructure architects
infrastructure right it's not only
technical the domain what the platform
they use but it's a domain-specific
platform so it is not only about
communication and and databases it is
also about for example the e-commerce
domain about automotive domain there are
specifics there are customer
requirements that get down to the domain
engineering to the platform and have an
impact there okay but we will discuss
this topic in subsequent episodes right
another thing that I want to distinguish
is are the roles of the architect versus
the role of the technical project lead
is this the same person or or do you see
any difference there yeah sometimes it's
explicitly defined like that at least in
in my environment and in other cases the
lead architect of our project is then de
facto basically the technical project
lead being asked for all the tasks
technical questions and in a project but
this is also a scalability thing I mean
if you have a project with ten
developers you don't in at least in my
opinion you don't need a technical
project lead an architect or more than
one architects and so of course the
thing is completely different if you
have a project with 200 developers I
mean go ahead yeah no okay scaling in
our case I mean I think it's obvious
that a three-person project can't be
done the same way as a 200 person
project and we'll probably discuss that
in subsequent episodes so in this the
architect also has does he have to deal
with politics and all that you know for
sure stuff for sure I mean an architect
has or one of the major points an
architect has to do is communicate with
the developers communicate with the
project manager and/or the cast
even the customer if you have some
functional stuff you you that affect the
architecture sometimes it's better to
change the requirements a bit to get a
much better architecture and therefore
speed and even the customer does want
this change in requirement so politics
communication is maybe at least as
important as technical knowledge to me
for an architect for me the technical
project leader or software architect is
the one who should be most concerned
about the technical soundness and the
proper technical goals and he should
preferably stay out of politics and when
he gets into politics he should vote for
the system care for for the technology
care for the the sound architectural
decisions and and try to minimize all of
course personal interests so you say
that the technical architect the
architect should say from a
non-political stat point of view this is
the way we should go and if you managers
want to override this decision because
you think there is some political stuff
we have to do then it's your decision
it's your responsibility
but I as a technical person I'll say do
it this way I would prefer that way I
know that it's a tough way but that is
the the the way I went in the past I had
a lot of trouble with this way but at
the end I had always a clean mind at
least and right the point I always do it
this I try to do it the same way and if
it if I'm involved with too much
politics I'll leave the project being a
freelance consultant back into maybe not
the best solution for the project but it
really depends I mean a frustrated
Marco's on a project leaving a broad
check that just makes a point I mean
this tells the project don't go on like
that but you just mentioned the the
politics in well the to the direction
customer or management or whatever I
don't think that is the only kind of
politics you have to deal with as an
architect because you also have
developers and UI designers and
requirement engineers whatever you have
to deal with a may be a huge team and
every every yea large group of people
has politics within so I still think an
architect should have the sense for
politics and and human interactions and
communications but it's that it's that
the same I mean yeah I agree that an
architect should be able to work with
people and coach people and communicate
people and maybe also resolve you know
if members of the team get on top of
each other and then fight some some
stuff out that the architect should be
able to resolve that but I mean that's
not what I would call politics that
depends on your definition of politics
of course for me it is politics too but
that's the definition thing for me that
would be management of a team and
politics is really you know this stuff
that you go to the customer and
basically I said that's a definition
thing I think we agree on this
human interaction thing we have to deal
a lot with people as an architect even
more than with technology in my opinion
and you have to have the skills I mean
that's one of the point why I think the
best programmer might be an not so good
architect because you have to have more
abilities than just architecture or
technical stuff if that doesn't work if
you have the best architecture in mind
and can't communicate it to your team or
get the team to implement implement it
too much too too big of an ego and
therefore accept always is right exactly
all these social skills have said things
are very very important for our hitters
in my opinion yeah okay until now we've
been talking about what the architect
does once the project or the
implementation has started is there
stuff for the architect to do before the
project really starts like in the areas
of requirements or estimating the amount
of money it costs or assembling the team
maybe hiring people so any things the
architect should do in these phases yeah
my believe in my understanding the
architect should be involved as early as
possible and the architect should
question the requirements very much so
when the architect doesn't understand or
doesn't have the feeling that there are
sufficient requirements available he
won't be able to communicate the the
design or design goals or generally the
requirements to the development team so
in any case when for example a system
gets developed and the project starts
with no requirements only weak
requirements I would actually expect the
architect to do the requirements
engineering to talk to the customer to
talk to management to all the
stakeholders and and get the
requirements straight
I agree although that's something that
many architects especially the more
technical minds don't really like to do
and that's also where I might want to
throw in a small anecdote about the role
of the architect and politics when I was
working for a big consulting company a
while ago we
to do an estimation for for a project
and we came up with I don't know 20
million or something and so it was a
rather big number and and then there was
management and said oh you know that's
too expensive we have to have oh at most
12 million so please reduce your
estimations so of course we didn't and
then of course that was where politics
came in we offered the project with
about 12 million and the customer
accepted and then of course we had
roughly 8 million overrun
isn't there a term for that designed to
cost or something like that
designed to cost actually anyway just
just an anecdote it's the architect also
responsible for building the team what
do you do as an architect if you see the
team isn't appropriate or there are
folks in the team who who aren't up to
the to the challenge no don't ask those
tough questions I think this is really a
tough one because if you as the
architect see that one of the problems
in a project is that you have some
people who aren't up to the job what do
you do I mean but that's highly
dependent on the project and the
organization you work the alternatives
well of course you could just talk to
the guy you have a problem with maybe
you you can coach him whatever otherwise
and most probably you you already did
this at this point so it didn't work
you can talk to you the project manager
about the decision of staffing if it's
possible to exchange and whatever I mean
the the organization maybe even the
project manager has not the right to
exchange people there so should this be
possible for an architect to exchange
people if necessary no not in my know I
agree with that he shouldn't be
shouldn't have to right to do it so it
should be the problem it should be the
responsibility of the the project
manager to project lead but I mean the
architect is the one who who can best
charge the technical abilities the
technical
whether whether a person is in the right
position in in a project and when he has
a gut feeling that this doesn't work
should talk to the project manager and
and try to find a position within the
project that this person this developer
could fulfill best his his or her job
that leads to this this organization
where you have two or three people who
do the real work then you have another
two or three people who help to help
those people to do the real work and
then you have this other set of people
who do something so that they have
something to do not not know it doesn't
have anybody that obviously it's a bit
provoking yeah and it doesn't have to be
that way I mean there are things that
are important and just require different
skill set I mean talking to customers
doing maintenance doing UI design for
examples very important thing and I know
a lot of developers great technical guys
who have a lot of trouble with doing
good UI design so you're very at least
under the larger projects or project
teams you really often have work to do
that is important and you just have to
find the right person for it so I
wouldn't be so negative on this pond
okay I mean and I don't fire people all
the time it's just I wanted to provoke
the discussion no of course in some time
I have sometimes I'd have to I mean it's
it's clear not everybody is OK for a
software project and can do it so
sometimes you have to of course yeah I
mean especially in highly critical and
projects with a very tough timeline you
have very little time to argue whether
this person is right in this position or
not and here it's a really problematic
and ethical question how how to deal
with that but still I think it's not the
question an architect should answer an
architect should give an indication if
somebody is not good in his job and
maybe or he should also give a hint
where he could do a good job but he
shouldn't do
this decision stuff I mean an architect
has to have some relationship with the
developers and if he just throws our
people out of the team it's much harder
to work in the team together yeah
yeah I totally agree I mean you need to
have trust as an architect developers
need to trust you you need to be able to
trust the developers to be a good team
else it doesn't work and you're you're
no longer an architect because the
architect
well defines itself by the team by the
developers and when you're not accepted
you're just not the architect even
though you might call you the you might
call yourself being the architect okay
so I think this basically concludes the
first episode on software architecture
in our series to give a small outlook
we'll probably discuss some
architectural patterns in subsequent
episodes we'll look at the quality
attributes architectures realized we'll
look at how to document architectures
and also at how to scale the
architectural process up to larger
projects and bigger team sizes and then
of course we'll have episodes on product
lines and all that stuff but that's a
separate topic it's not going to be
under the name of software architecture
anything else you want to say Mikael or
Alex good luck with your next software
design ok then thanks and see you next
week or in ten days actually bye bye bye
[Laughter]
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning party for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]